<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lawes and ordinances touching military discipline Set downe and established the 13. of August. 1590. Translated into English by I. D.</title>
            <title>Articulbrief ofte ordonnantie op de discipline militaire. English</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120998</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21716</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21716)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1636:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lawes and ordinances touching military discipline Set downe and established the 13. of August. 1590. Translated into English by I. D.</title>
                  <title>Articulbrief ofte ordonnantie op de discipline militaire. English</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
                  <author>Huygens, Christiaan, 1551-1624.</author>
                  <author>I. D., fl. 1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the widowe &amp; heires of the deceased Hillebrand Iacobs van Wouw, ordinarie printer to the high and mightie Lords the Stats Generall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at the Haghe :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of:  Articulbrief ofte ordonnantie op de discipline militaire.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: By order of the Councell of State. Chr. Huyghens.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-B4).</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum privilegio.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LAWES AND ORDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances touching military diſcipline. Set downe and eſtabliſhed the 13. of Auguſt. 1590.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſh by I. D.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at the Haghe by the widowe &amp; heires of the deceaſed Hille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand Iacobs van Wouw, Ordinarie Printer to the high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lords the Stats Generall. Anno 1631. <hi>Cum Privilegie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="list_of_laws">
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, many diſorders are found, to growe amongſt thoſe that beare armes, tending to the great damage of theſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the gouverneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are not any where ſo puniſhed as in reaſon they ought, becauſe there is no certaine order, or lawe touching like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as yet decreed and publiſhed: The States general of the vnyted Provinces have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (with th'advyce of the Councel of State of the ſame) ordayned, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and decreed, doe by theſe preſents ordayne, appoint, and decree the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or laws here enſuing, which their wil is, to have from point to point ſtrictly obſerved and followed by all thoſe that beare armes in their ſervice, To which ende it ſhalbe every where publiſhed, and accordingly ſworne to by the ſouldiours.</p>
            <p n="1">I. FIrſt he that ſhal take the Lordes name in vayne, or blaſpheme the ſame, ſhal for the firſt tyme make an honorable amends, and be kept three dayes in priſon at bread and water: The ſeconde tyme ſhal have a glowing iron thruſt through his tongue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſtripped to his ſhirte, and ſo baniſhed out of the vnyted Provinces.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The like penalty ſhal they incurre, for the firſt and ſecond tymes, who ſhal eyther doe or ſay ought in deſpyte, or deriſion of Gods worde, or the Miniſters of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">III. All wilfull murthers, rapes, adultery, fyring of houſes, the very, violence, outrage, falſhood, and other like bad facts, and open offenſes, or vnnaturall abuſes, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. None ſhall any way outrage, ſtryke, knocke, beate, threaten or diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly touch any widowes, maryed or vnmaryed wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch as are in childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or with child, nor any young children, on paine to be diſcharged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money or paſporte, or els puniſhed corporally according to the quality of the offenſe. Likewyſe all common whores ſhal for the firſt tyme bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed out of the Campe with ſhame, and being founde there the ſecond tyme, ſoundly whipped and baniſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:3"/>
            <p n="5">V. He that ſhal have done or conſpyred ought againſt the States, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Townes, or other places thereof, or againſt any Governours, or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in the ſame, whereby the publique ſtate of the Land may be in any ſort endammaged, or endangered: as alſo whoſoever ſhal conſent therevnto, ſhal without any mercie bee hanged.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The like puniſhment ſhal they alſo incurre, whoſoever coming to the knowledge of any ſuch matter, ſhall not reveale it to their Captaine, or chieff Officers.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. None ſhall rayſe any mutiny, or make any vnlawful aſſembly, on what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſecret, cloaked, or other purpoſes: nor for what cauſe ſoever it be, without order fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Commaunders, on paine of hanging.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. In like ſort ſhal they alſo bee puniſhed, that ſhalbe preſent at ſuch aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, or call, ſtir vp, and incite any to be preſent thereat. And is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood alſo, that ſuch Officers as ſhalbe at the lyke ſeditious meetings, ſhall receyve puniſhement before all other ſouldiours, except thoſe (that are noe authors thereof)</p>
            <p n="9">IX. He that ſhall ſpeake ill of the States generall, or particular, the Councel of State, or other Superiours, or ſhall ſpeake ought to deſpite or deride any of them, ſhal without mercy be puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="10">X. He that ſhal have ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any wordes tending to ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mutiny, or diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or that having heard ſuch wordes, and ſhal not preſently acquaint his Cap. therewith, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. In like ſorte ſhal they alſo be puniſhed, who rehearſe any ſuch words in preſence of private ſouldiours, eyther of themſelves, or by ſuggeſtion of others, or practiſe ought, whereby any mutiny or ſedition may growe.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. No man, be yt out of garded, or beſieged places, or in other like caſes, ſhal vſe any ſpeach or correſpondence with the enemie, nor ſend him any meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or Letters, nor receive any from him, nor deale in like ſorte with any of his confederates, bee it in ſecrete or publicque, without the conſent firſt had of his Gouvernour or Cap. or that he make it foorthwith knowne vnto him, vnleſſe he be thereto aucthoriſed. Neyther ſhall any man be adherent or in
<pb facs="tcp:21716:3"/>any ſorte aſſiſtant to the enemy, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Likewyſe none ſhal conferre or converſe with any Trompet or Drumme of the enemyes, or any other ſent on meſſage from him, but they onely who are thereto appointed, on paine of death.</p>
            <p n="14">XIIII. None ſhall in going, departing, lying ſtill, muſtering, or in garniſon doe ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trage or ſpoyle to the inhabitants of theſe Countreys, their favorours or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, or take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them any victuals, money, or ought els, without paying duely for the ſame, nor yet throw downe, or ſpoyle any water-mils or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-works, nor ſet on fyre the ſame, or other houſes, or els the campe, at the breaking vp thereof, without ſpecial commaund fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the General, or other Chiefe Officer, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Like wyſe none ſhal eyther doe or practiſe ought againſt any perſons, Townes, Villages, Forts, Havens, or whatſoever goods warranted by paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes or other aſſurances from the Generality, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. He that wil departe from one Company to another, or elſwhere, or will leave the Colours vnder which he ſerveth, is to have a ſufficient paſport from his Cap. or Commaunder, and fayling therein, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Whatſoever Cap. ſhall entertayne ſouldiours without a lawfull diſcharge from their former Cap. ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. If any ſouldiour (ſerving on horſſe or foote) ſhal knock or ſtryke his hoſt, hoſteſſe, their man or mayde-ſervant, he ſhal for the firſt tyme be kept three dayes at bread and water, the ſecond, make an honourable amendes, and before the whole watch bee diſarmed, and then baniſhed out of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, And if the party ſo ſtriken be maimed, or bloud drawne, then ſhal the ſouldiour offending have his hand ſtriken of.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. Whoſoever ſhal have taken or ſtolne any victuals, or other proviſions brought vp, towards the Camp, Garniſon, or any Towns, or places vnder the juriſdiction of the States generall, ſhalbee hanged.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. Likewyſe none ſhal out of the Campe or Garniſon forcibly take or els buy vp before hande, any victuals or goods bound thitherwardes, before the ſame ſhalbe brought to a fit place for ſale, and taxed: Neyther ſhall he
<pb facs="tcp:21716:4"/>robbe any cabbin, ſhop, tent, Victualer, or Marchand that is there for the helpe of the Campe or Garniſon, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. He that ſhal goe out of the quarter from his Colours, or Garniſon, further then a Canon-ſhot, without his Cap. leave, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. Whoſoever ſhal goe out of the Campe, beſieged towne, fort or other place, without the ſpeciall conſent of his Cap. or Officer, for any cauſe, bee it for forrage or ought els, ſhalbee hanged.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. Whoſoever ſhal take any Cattaile, or beaſts within the landes that lye vnder the obedience of the Generality, ſhalbee puniſhed as a Theife.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIIII. He that in marching by lande towardes the fielde, or in retourning thence, ſhal forſake his Colours or Cornet, ſhall without any mercy be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. And whoſoever (not being viſited with manifeſt ſicknes, and theſame knowne to his Cap. or Commaunder) ſhal keepe along with the baggage, or ryde on the waggons, ſhalbe diſarmed before the whole Company, and then baniſhed without money or paſport.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. If any ſhal neglect his watch, or other ſervice committed vnto him, he ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. If any ſouldiour ſhalbe founde ſleeping on his ſentinel, he ſhall without any mercy be puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. Whatſoever ſouldiour ſhal, eyther by day or night departe from his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinel, where he hath bene placed by his Corporall, vnles he be called thence, or relieved by the ſaid Corporall, ſhall receive puniſhment of death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mercy.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. None ſhal declare or make knowne the watch-word to the enemy, or any other, nor give any other worde then is given him by the Officer, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. Whoſoever ſhal abſent himſelfe out of the Courte of garde above two houres in the day tyme, or any with in the night without his Corporals
<pb facs="tcp:21716:4"/>leave, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. None ſhal without lawful cauſe rayſe any tumult, or alarme, nor diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge a piece by night, nor make any noyſe, nor doe ought els, where by the ſame may growe (without cauſe) on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. He that ſhall preſume within the Campe, Quarter, or place, where he lyeth in garniſon, as alſo after the watch is ſet, to drawe his weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feict his lyfe: as alſo yf he do it out of the Camp, Towne, or place, without leave of his Officer.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. He that ſhall ſtryke any man with his ſworde vndrawne, or with a cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, ſtone, or otherwyſe, that bloude followe, ſhal looſe his hande.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIIII. He that ſhal give any one a boxe on the eare, ſhal in preſence of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany take the lyke boxe agayne of the party ſo wronged, and beſydes be diſarmed and baniſhed the Company.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. No ſouldiours ſhal without order from their Chiefs, Captaines, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders hold any common meeting or gathering together, bee it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund money or ought els, nor yet be preſent at ſuch aſſemblies, on payne of death. Provyded always, that ſuch Capt. or Commaunders as ſhal ſuffer the ſame to happen at vndue ſeaſons, and in vnlawfulwiſe, ſhall (for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others) bee puniſhed with death before all the ſouldiours.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. If any ſhall call for money as they are marching in the face of the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or vpon any enterpriſe, they ſhal receive puniſhment of death without any mercy.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. Iff yt chance that the Monethly entertainement bee not payed on the very day, or that it cannot bee ſent vnto the ſouldiours for ſome cauſe, be it through any hinderance of the enemy, or otherwiſe, none ſhall therefore make any tumult, or ſpeake ſeditious wordes, or ſeeke to force his Captaine to the payment thereof, neyther yet any whit the leſſe diſcharge and haue care of his marches and watches, but contenting him ſelfe with a reaſonable loane, vntil the money become, or maye come ſhall fully performe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie required of a good ſouldiour. And whoſoever doth the contrarie, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth thoſe that doe it, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:5"/>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. No Captaines, Lieutenants, or Enſignes ſhal departe out of the place where their Companies lye in garniſon, whether it bee to ſolicite for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſaid Companies, or for their owne buſines, without leave of their Commaunder or Governour, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. He that ſhal in anie quarrell, fight, or otherwiſe call thoſe of his nation to helpe, or gather an aſſemblie, ſhalbe hanged.</p>
            <p n="40">XL. He that ſhalbe found by day or night out of the campe or place beſieged, without his Captaines leave, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. Whoſoever ſhal goe on fre-booting, and commit ſpoyles, extorſions, and theft, ſhalbe hanged.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. If one ſouldiour chalenge another into the fielde, without leave from him that commaundes in that quarter, hee ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. If any Corporal or other commaunding the watch, ſhall ſuffer towe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours to goe foorth to fighte, he ſhall without mercy be puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIIII. Any ſouldiour being wronged by worde or deede he ſhall repayre to him that commaundes in the quarter, who after the hearing of both partyes ſhall cauſe ſatiſfaction of the wrong to be made vnto the party intereſſed, with bare heade, and in preſence of the whole watch: And yf he finde cauſe, ſhal alſo diſarme the wrongdoer, and baniſh him out of the Company.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. And yf there bee no witnes of the quarell, then ſhall the ſayde Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cauſe the partyes to agree in his preſence, whereto yf they will not condeſcende, then both, or hee that denyes it, ſhalbe diſarmed and baniſhed out of the Company.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. Whatſoever ſouldiour or Commaunder ſhal goe out of the camp, Towne, or fort, or enter thereinto by any other way, then at the ports and and ordinary entrances, ſhalbe hanged.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. If any ſouldiour ſhall refuſe the commaund of his Cap. or any other, who commaundes over him in the ſeruice of the States General, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="tcp:21716:5"/>theſame, hee ſhalbe puniſhed with death: as hee like wyſe ſhal, who tranſgreſſeth any off the Generals commaundements publiſhed by ſound of dromme or trompet.</p>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. At the ſounding of any alarme every one ſhall reſorte to his Enſigne, or Cornet, and whoſoever comes not thither (vnleſſe it be on apparant neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) or runnes to an other place without conſent and ſpeciall order from his Commaunder, or comes not ſo ſoone as his Enſigne, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. Every ſouldiour ſhal ayde and defende his Coulours by day and night, and on the firſt warning repayre vnto them, not departing thence, vntill it bee brought into a place of ſafety, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="50">L. If any ſhal depart out of the order, or rancke wherein he is placed, vnleſſe it bee on neceſſary occaſions, and that he hath therewith acquaynted his Officer, hee ſhalbee puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. Hee that ſhall firſt beginne to flye in a battaile or aſſault, may lawfully be ſlayne thereupon by any one: And yf he eſcape, hee ſhalbee declared a villayne, and receive puniſhment of death without mercy.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. None that is appoynted to the defenſe of any breach, trenche, or ſkonce, bee it Cap. or Souldiour, ſhall willingly forſake the ſame, or through any falſe or couloured occaſions, or excuſes abſent himſelfe from thence, without ſufficient order, or warrant allowed by the Councel of warre, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. None ſhal ſurrender or deliver to th'enemy any place, the keeping whereof is commitred vnto him, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="54">LIIII. Likewyſe none ſhal runne from his quarter in a beſieged place, cry for compoſition, or ſpeake thereof, bee vnwilling to fighte, labour, or defende their quarter, or make others vnwilling therevnto, or doe ought els in ſuch a place, whereby the defenſe thereof may be hindered, on payne of death without any mercy.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. If any man runne away to th'enemy, or in ſuch his flight bee taken by th'enemy, hee ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:6"/>
            <p n="56">LVI. No Captaines ſhall ſeduce, or intyce away each others Souldiours, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. Whoſoever ſhal by word or deede buſy himſelfe with the Sergeant Maior doing his office, bee hee Captaine or Souldiour, ſhal without mercy be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with death: As he alſo ſhal, who wil not content himſelfe with that quarter, or lodging, whereto he ſhalbe appoynted by the Quartermaſter or Furrier, or who will diſturbe another man in his place.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. If any ſouldiour having the wacth, ſhal come to his Colours not fully ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to march with the reſt vnto the watch, he ſhall for the firſt tyme, bee kept three dayes at breade and water: the ſecond, diſarmed and baniſhed for three Moneths out of the Company, and the third tyme ſuffer death.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. Every one, of what condition ſoever he bee, ſhall foorthwith or before the evening bring before him that commaundes in the quarter, al ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners as ſhalbe taken of th'enemy, on payne of forfeicting the ſayde priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to bee puniſhed beſydes with death.</p>
            <p n="60">LX. And yf any ſhall take priſoner a Generall, Commaunder, or other man of accompt of th'enemy, he is foorthwith to preſent, or cauſe to bee preſented the ſayd priſoner vnto the States generall or Councell of State, and with-all to deliver him over, as alſo whatſoever other priſoners they wil take to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, receyving therefore a reaſonable rewarde according to the quality and ability of the priſoner: provyded that it exceede not the ſomme of 5000. gilderns: And ſo the ſayd priſoner ſhalbe at the diſpoſing of th'aforeſayd States, and he that tooke him, pretende no farther intereſt in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="61">LXI. Likewiſe none ſhal kil any priſoner, or ſet his ranſome, or after the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſayd ranſome, ſuffer him to departe without leave of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or him that commaundes in the quarter, on payne of being diſarmed, and baniſhed out of theſe Countreys.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. And yf any priſoners bee founde, walking along the Campe or place of garniſon, without leave of the General, or him that commaundes there, he to whom the priſoner belongeth, ſhall forfeicte him to thoſe, who ſhal firſt lay handes on the ſayd priſoner.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:6"/>
            <p n="63">LXIII. Concerning lawful pryzes, whoſoeuer bring in the ſame, ſhall acquaynte therewith the Generall, or him that commaundes in the quarter, within three houres after their retourne, to th'ende they may bee accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, on payne of forfeicting theſame, and to be beſydes puniſhed on the bodie.</p>
            <p n="64">LXIIII. Whoſoever ſhal haue gotten any thing vpon the enemy, and giveth not notice thereof as aforeſayde, that it may be regiſtred, and after ſolde in the Campe or place of garniſon, but ſhall ſel, or cauſe it to bee ſolde in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or townes neare therevnto, ſhall without any mercy bee puniſhed with death, to th'ende that better order be held in all, and no man wronged in his righte.</p>
            <p n="65">LXV. When a ſouldiour ſhall have done any offenſe or faulte, his Captaine ſhalbe bounde (on payne of three moneths ſuſpenſion from his charge) to deliver the ſayd ſouldiour into the Generals handes, or his that commaundes in the quarter, who with the Captames, Lieutenants, and Enſignes then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſhal vpon th'information, which hee ſhal cauſe to be taken thereof, judge according to theſe orders and lawes.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. He that is droncke on his watch-day, ſhalbe caſſiered, and baniſhed out of the Company.</p>
            <p n="67">LXVII. Item yf any one drincke himſelfe druncke, and in his drunckenneſſe commit any ill or ought forbidden, hee ſhal not thereby bee excuſed, but ſo much the more ſharpely puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. If any Cap. or ſouldiour ſhall refuſe the muſter or reviewe, hee ſhalbe caſſiered.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. None ſhal at the muſter let himſelfe be entred by a changed, or other name, then his owne, nor paſſe muſter with a borrowed horſſe or armes: neyther ſhal any on the muſterday lende the like, on payne of being diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and baniſhed out of the Company.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. None ſhal let himſelfe be entred, or muſter vnder towe Companis, on payne of death.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21716:7"/>
            <p n="71">LXXI. None ſhal diminiſch or pawne his armes, which are appointed him by his Captaine, on payne of being diſarmed, and baniſhed for ſixe moneths out of the Company.</p>
            <p n="72">LXXII. None ſhal likewyſe take or pawne any ſouldiours armes, on payne of looſing double the worth of the pawne.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. None ſhal play away or quyte his armes, but keepe theſame alwayes cleane and ſerviceable, on payne of being caſſiered out of the Company without paſport.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIIII. None ſhall by couſenage get away his fellowes proviſions, victuals, or armes, on payne of being diſarmed, and baniſhed for three moneths out of the Company, or els beſydes, of ſuſtaining corporal puniſhment according to the quality of th'offenſe.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. He that ſhal preſume to ſet vpon a Commiſſary of the muſters, or wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him either in word or deede, ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. If any Captaine give his ſouldiours leſſe then the pay allowed him by the States, he ſhalbe diſgraded.</p>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. If any ſouldiour proffer to drawe his weapon againſt his Chief, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder, he ſhalbe puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. If the Provoſt or his Officers apprehende one or more ſouldiours, none (of what degree ſoever) ſhall oppoſe himſelfe thereagainſt, or reſkewe, or attempt to reſkewe the ſayd priſoners, on payne of death.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. Furthermore, no Officer nor Gentleman of any Company, of horſſe or foote, nor any common ſouldiour ſhal victuaile in any Camp, without the Generals ſpecial conſent, on payne of being diſarmed.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. Likewyſe al Victualers that victual in the Campe, ſhalbe ſubject to th'aforeſaid articles and the Councel of warre there being, on the penalty here in contayned, and ſhall not draw any wyne or beere for any one in the evening, an houre after the Sunnes ſetting, or in the morning aſmuch before the ryſing thereof, on payne of forfeicting 3 gilderns for every tyme they
<pb facs="tcp:21716:7"/>ſhalbe founde to have done ſo: the ſayd forfeict to be converted, th'one halfe to the Provoſts behoofe, and th'other to the reliefe of the poore.</p>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. Al other abuſes and offenſes not ſpecifyed in thſe Orders, ſhalbe puniſhed according to the ordinances, lawes, and cuſtomes of the warre.</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. And yf any ſouldiours ſhould not bee preſent at the proclayming of theſe orders and lawes, they ſhall notwithſtanding bee aſmuch bounde to th'obſervation of them as the other who were preſent. But to th'ende none may pretende ignorance, and every one have notice thereof, the States ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall have given order, that theſame ſhalbee every where publiſhed on the muſter-day, and charged the Commiſſaries to cauſe all the ſouldiours to ſweare accordingly therevnto.</p>
            <p>THus done and decreed at Arnhem after ſundry conferences had here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon with the chiefeſt Commaunders of theſe vnited Provinces. It being farther appoynted, that theſe orders and lawes ſhalbe publiſhed both in the Campe, and whereſoever els it ſhalbe meete and requiſite, and that at every muſter the Commiſſaries ſhal reade, and propound the ſame agarne vnto the Companies. The 13. of Auguſt 1590.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By order of the Councell of State.
Chr. Huyghens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
